Register of the Poland. Ministerstwo Spraw Zagranicznych Records, 1919-1947.
Hoover Institution Archives
- SERIES NO. 245.2. PRISONERS OF WAR. See also SERIES NOS. 790 and 793
  - 1941. Polish POWs
    - Germany
      - Switzerland
        - Polish diplomatic mission to (Folder 22)
      - Y.M.C.A. Report on shipment of parcels from Warsaw (Folder 23)
    - Soviet Union
      - General (Folder 24)
      - Iran. Evacuation channels (Folder 25)
  - 1942
    - French Foreign Legion (Folder 26)
    - French POWs (Folder 27)
    - Poland
      - Arrests of army reserve officers (Folder 28)
      - Hostages taken by Germans (Folder 29)
    - Poles in German army
      - Conditions of recruitment (Folder 30)
      - Outline of governments policy toward (Folder 31)
      - Press reports (Folder 32)
      - Soviet Union. Polish government's intervention on behalf of Polish POWs (Folder 33)
    - Polish POWs in Finland (Folder 34)
    - Polish POWs in Germany
      - Books for prisoners (Folder 35)
      - Locations of camps (Folder 36)
      - Parcels
        - Belgium (Folder 37)
        - France (Folder 38)
        - Polish Red Cross. Rome branch (Folder 39)
        - South America (Folder 40)
        - Turkey (Folder 41)
      - Reports of former prisoners (Folder 42)
      - Status of prisoners and living conditions in camps (Folder 43)
      - Switzerland
        - Bern Legation. Assistance (Folder 44)
        - Deserters (Folder 45)
        - Escapees (Folder 46)
        - Red Cross (Folder 47)
    - Recruitment of persons of non-Allied nationality into Allied Forces. Memorandum of British government (Folder 48)
    - Soviet POWs
      - General (Folder 49)
      - 1943 (Folder 100)
      - Poles serving in Red army, in German captivity (Box 50)
    - Palestine. Rumors on Jewish POWs (Folder 1)
    - Poles in German army
      - General (Folder 2)
      - African front. Report on recruitment (Folder 3)
      - Canada, Polish POWs in (Folder 4)
      - Draft certificate for Poles willing to join Polish army (Folder 5)
      - France. Intervention of government on behalf of (Folder 6)
      - Legal status of deportees and internees (Folder 7)
      - Intervention to British authorities (Folder 8)
      - London government
        - Action (Folder 9)
        - Reports (Folder 10)
      - Negotiations with Americans and Canadians on recruitment into Polish army (Folder 11)
      - Soviet Union. Captivity (Folder 12)
      - Vatican. Deserter Augustyn Filusz (Folder 13)
    - Poles in Soviet army (Folder 14)
    - Polish POWs in Germany
      - Books for (Folder 15)
      - Conditions in camps (Folder 16)
      - Irish initiative to provide assistance to former Polish prisoner Zaslaw Krzywoblocki (Folder 17)
      - Jewish prisoners (Folder 18)
      - Legal defense for prisoners. Geneva Convention, 1929 (Folder 19)
      - Parcels
        - Africa (Folder 20)
        - Australia (Folder 21)
        - Canada (Folder 22)
        - Great Britain (Folder 23)
        - Ireland (Folder 24)
        - Italy (Folder 25)
        - Middle East (Folder 26)
        - Portugal (Folder 27)
        - South America (Folder 28)
        - Spain (Folder 29)
        - Sweden (Folder 30)
        - United States
          - General (Folder 31)
          - Lend-lease (Folder 32)
      - Spiritual assistance (Folder 33)
      - Sweden. Release of Polish internees (Folder 34)
      - Switzerland. Red Cross (Folder 35)
      - Y.M.C.A. Report on conditions in German camps (Folder 36)
    - Soviet POWs in Germany (Folder 37)
    - Sweden. Press reports on conditions in German camps, by Johannes Wickman. Typescript (Folder 38)
  - 1944
    - General (Folder 39)
    - British POWs in Poland (Folder 40)
    - Poles in German army
      - Bitterfeld camp (Folder 41)
      - British authorities. Intervention on behalf of (Folder 42)
      - Italian front reports (Folder 43)
    - Polish POWs in Germany (Folder 44)
    - Soviet POWs in France (Folder 45)
- SERIES NO. 245.3. ECONOMIC ORGANIZATION OF POST-WAR EUROPE
  - 1940. Inter-Allied Governments Conference. Declaration (Box 101, Folder 1)
  - 1942. Post-war planning
    - Borders
      - Correspondence between Viscount Cecil and Tytus Filipowicz (Folder 2)
      - Council of Ministers. Resolution (Folder 3)
      - Western borders
        - General (Folder 4)
        - Government plan as reported by J. Zaleski (Folder 5)
        - Maps (Folder 6)
    - Central Europe
      - General (Folder 7)
      - Ministerstwo Spraw Kongresowych
        - "Ogolne zasady organizacji Europy Srodkowo-Wschodniej". Typescript (Folder 8)
        - "Sprawa Europy Srodkowo-Wschodniej". Memorandum (Folder 9)
        - "Sprawa Europy Srodkowej i Poludniowo Wschodniej". Mimeograph (Folder 10)
      - Ministry of Foreign Affairs
        - Response to concept of federated Eastern Europe as presented in "Ogolne zasady" (Folder 11)
        - "The Problem of Central and Southeastern Europe". Typescript (Folder 12)
    - Economy
      - General (Folder 13)
      - Agricultural and peasant program by representatives of 7 central and southeastern European countries (Folder 14)
      - Bibliography on economic literature (Folder 15)
      - British assistance (Folder 16)
      - Governments economic policy. Decisions made before Conference of Royal Institute of International Affairs (Folder 17)
      - Government's economic committee (Folder 18)
      - Joint declaration on transfer of property in territories occupied by Axis powers. Typescript (Folder 19)
      - Maritime Council (Folder 20)
      - Ministry of Treasury. Report on post-war planning, Jan 1, 1941-June 24, 1942 (Folder 21)
      - "Projekt tez w sprawie miedzynarodowej sytuacji gospodarczej Polski". Typescript (Folder 22)
      - Property rights (Folder 23)
      - Public transportation (Folder 24)
      - Supplies and purchases (Folder 25)
      - United States assistance (Folder 26)
    - Federation plans
      - General (Folder 27)
      - Germany. Blueprint of Nazi European Empire (Folder 28)
      - Great Britain
        - General (Folder 29)
        - Government sources (Folder 30)
      - Netherlands (Folder 31)
      - Switzerland (Folder 32)
      - United States (Folder 33)
    - Germany
      - "Poland and Germany and the Post-War Reconstruction of Europe". Proofs, corrections and comments (Folder 34)
      - Polish government policy toward Germany. Note for the minister by legal adviser Potulicki (Folder 35)
      - "Polska a Niemcy". Paper by Ministerstwo Spraw Kongresowych. Typescript (Folder 36)
    - Government agencies (Box 102)
      - Biuro Zagadnien Powojennych, New York (Folder 1)
      - "Cele wojny polskiej a drogi ich osiagniecia" by Zofia Zaleska. Mimeograph (Folder 2)
      - "O nowy porzadek rzeczy". Typescript (Folder 3)
      - "Polskie cele wojny" by Marian Seyda. Post-war prognosis (Folder 4)
      - Rada Narodowa (National Council). Plenary sessions, Lecture of Marian Seyda at (Folder 5)
    - "United Nations and the Organization of Peace". Typescript (Folder 6)
    - United States
      - Commission to Study the Organization of Peace. Intelligence report (Folder 7)
      - Ministerstwo Prac Kongresowych. Commander Agar's speech at London International Assembly (Folder 8)
  - 1943
    - Allied Military Government (Folder 9)
    - Borders
      - Czechoslovakia (Folder 10)
      - Ministerstwo Prac Kongresowych
        - "Linia z dnia 8 XII 1919 i linia Curzona z 11 VII 1920". Typescript (Folder 11)
        - "Memorandum on the Curzon Line" by Polish Research Centre, London. Mimeograph (Folder 12)
        - "Problem of Plebiscites". Mimeograph (Folder 13)
        - "Ziemie Wschodnie Polski". Report. Mimeograph (Folder 14)
    - Canada
      - List of available literature on post-war reconstruction (Folder 15)
      - "Post-War Reconstruction for Canada: Organization and Problems" by Cyril James. Typescript (Folder 16)
      - "Principles of Post-War Cooperation". Speech by MacKenzie King (Folder 17)
    - Central European Federation
      - "Concept of Federalism in Eastern Europe in Historic Perspective". Chapter of large publication (author unknown). Typescript (Folder 18)
      - Henry Andrews Committee
        - General (Folder 19)
        - Proposal for group on joint economic interest (Folder 20)
      - Institute on Reconstruction of Central and Eastern Europe, Democratic Post-War Reconstruction in Central Eastern Europe, No. 1. Printed copy (Folder 21)
      - Soviet vision of federation (Folder 22)
    - Germany (Box 103)
      - "German Problem and Poland" by Jerzy Adamkiewicz. Typescript (Folder 1)
      - "Problem of Prussia". Mimeograph (Folder 2)
      - Reeducation of Germans (Folder 3)
      - "Transfer of Germans from Poland". Mimeograph (Folder 4)
    - Government agencies
      - General (Folder 5)
      - "Ameryka Lacinska a polski program pokojowy" by Stanislaw Fischl. Typescript (Folder 6)
      - "Cele wojny polskiej a drogi ich osiagniecia" by Zofia Zaleska. Mimeograph (Folder 7)
      - Churchill's speech of March 11. Official response (Folder 8)
      - Confirmation of receipt of documents sent to embassies (Folder 9)
      - "Deklaracja Ministra Edwarda Raczynskiego w Radzie Narodowej", March 16. Typescript (Folder 10)
    - Government agencies
      - Ministerstwo Pracy i Opieki Spolecznej. Dzial Rekonstrukcji Socjalnej. Biuletyn Informacyjny, Nos. 1-5 (Folder 11)
      - "Prace rzadu nad zagadnieniami gospodarki narodowej" by Jan Kwapiszewski. Mimeograph (Folder 12)
      - Questionnaires
        - Board of Trade. Foreign Office. Response (Folder 13)
        - Canada. Polish intellectuals on post-war Poland (Folder 14)
        - U.S. government official on situation in Poland (Folder 15)
      - United States
        - General (Folder 16)
        - American bishops (Folder 17)
        - Business circles (Folder 18)
        - Ministerstwo Prac Kongresowych. Delegatura (Folder 19)
        - Resolutions by Connally and Fulbright (Folder 20)
        - Training of American Administration for Europe (Folder 21)
        - War aims (Folder 22)
      - Various countries
        - Argentina (Folder 23)
        - Australia (Folder 24)
        - Chile (Folder 25)
        - China (Folder 26)
        - Colombia (Folder 27)
        - Great Britain
          - General (Folder 28)
          - National Peace Council (Folder 29)
          - New Europe Circle (Folder 30)
        - Norway (Folder 31)
        - Sweden (Folder 32)
        - 1944 (Box 104)
    - Central European Federation
      - Henry Andrews Committee (Folder 1)
      - Mid-European Federation (Folder 2)
      - Propaganda through Polish Press Agency (Folder 3)
    - Government agencies
      - General (Folder 4)
      - Instructions for embassies and consulates (Folder 5)
      - "The Post-War Aims of Poland". Compilation of speeches by Stanislaw Mikolajczyk (Folder 6)
      - War reparations (Folder 7)
    - Various countries
      - France. Free French (Folder 8)
      - Great Britain. "Reflections on the Economic Future of Europe". Speech by Samuel Hoare. Mimeograph (Folder 9)
      - Sweden. Bibliography of Swedish literature on post-war planning (Folder 10)
      - Turkey (Folder 11)
- SERIES NO. 245.4. WAR ATROCITIES
  - 1941
    - Conference des Representants des Pays Occupes par l'Ennemi, London, Nov. 5-21. Minutes of meetings
      - Copy 1 (Folder 12)
      - Copy 2 (Folder 13)
    - Declaration on German atrocities
      - General (Folder 14)
      - American refusal to sign (Folder 15)
      - Clippings from London press (Folder 16)
      - Declaration's text (Folder 17)
      - Declarations by
        - Raczynski, Edward, Ministry of Foreign Affairs (Folder 18)
        - Strassburger, Henryk, Ministry of Finance (Folder 19)
      - Diplomatic letters
        - Informing about initiative (Folder 20)
        - Responding to initiative (Folder 21)
      - History of initiative, by Michal Potulicki (Folder 22)
      - Joint Polish-Czechoslovak resolution (Folder 23)
      - Note to the minister (Folder 24)
      - Presentation of note to foreign governments (Folder 25)
      - Response to British proposition on "German guilt" (Folder 26)
      - Signing of declaration (Folder 27)
    - Inter-Allied Commission Against War Crimes. Minutes of meetings (Folder 28)
  - 1942
    - Government agencies
      - Polish War Crimes Office (Komisja Karania Zbrodni Wojennych). "Zagadnienie karania przestepstw wojennych". Typescript note (Folder 29)
      - Presidential decree on punishment of war crimes (Folder 30)
    - Inter-Allied Commission Against War Crimes. Minutes, November (Folder 31)
    - Inter-Allied Research Group (Groupement Interallie pour l'Etude des Activites des Allemands et de leurs Satellites). Minutes
      - German press on Germanization policy in Poland, 1940-1942. Polish government documentation (Folder 32)
      - Note de Bureau, Nos. 1-40 (Folder 33)
      - Note de Bureau, Nos. 41-54 (Folder 34)
      - Plenary meetings, September-December (Folder 35)
    - Saint James Palace Declaration (Box 105)
      - Introductory note (Folder 1)
      - "Punishment for War Crimes, 2". Proofs
        - Belgian copy (Folder 2)
        - Czech copy (Folder 3)
        - Polish copy (Folder 4)
    - United States. Roosevelt, F. D. Statements on war crimes of Aug. 21 and Oct. 7 (Folder 5)
  - 1943
    - General (Folder 5)
    - Canada. Press comments (Folder 6)
    - Comite Interallie Pour l'Etude de l'Armistice. Proces verbaux des seances. Documents. Premiere partie. Selection (Folder 7)
    - Government agencies
      - "German Persecution in Poland". Government report. Typescript (Folder 8)
      - Inter-Ministerial Conference on Punishment of War Crimes, Oct. 9 (Folder 9)
      - Lists and reports on war criminals (Folder 10)
      - Record keeping on witnesses and offenders (Folder 11)
      - Reports of witnesses (Folder 12)
      - Revenge on Germans. "Notatka w sprawach niemieckich", Apr. 8. Typescript (Folder 13)
    - India. Protest action against persecution of women in Poland and Czechoslovakia (Folder 14)
    - Inter-Allied Commission Against War Crimes
      - Circulated materials (Folder 15)
      - Correspondence (Folder 16)
      - Initiatives and cooperation with other agencies (Folder 17)
      - Minutes of meetings, Jan.-June (Folder 18)
      - Polish initiatives (Folder 19)
    - Inter-Allied Research Group (Groupement Interallie pour l'Etude des Activites des Allemands et de leurs Satellites) (Box 106)
      - Circulated materials (Folder 1)
      - German emigre circles in Great Britain (Folder 2)
      - Note de Bureau, Nos. 56-109 (Folder 3)
      - Plenary debates. Reports (Folder 4)
    - Saint James Palace Declaration
      - Collective note to Vatican (Folder 5)
      - Correspondence with diplomatic representatives (Folder 6)
      - Introductory note. Material for publication (Folder 7)
      - Polish government note (Folder 8)
      - "Zagadnienia karania przestepcow wojennych". Annotations and corrections. Typescript (Folder 9)
    - United Nations Commission for the Investigation of War Crimes, Founding of (Folder 10)
    - United States. Press clippings on post-war Germany and prosecution of war criminals (Folder 11)
    - War crimes. General issues
      - General (Folder 12)
      - Legal aspects of prosecution
        - Correspondence (Folder 13)
        - Notes and studies (Folder 14)
        - Publications and propaganda (Folder 15)
      - "War Crimes: A Legal Approach" by Manfred Lachs. Typescript (Folder 16)
    - Yugoslavia. German policy toward Slovenia (Folder 17)
    - 1944 (Box 107)
    - American Jewish Committee. War Crimes Commission. Majdanek concentration camp (Folder 1)
    - "Convention for the Surrender of War Criminals". Draft. Typescript (Folder 2)
    - Government agencies
      - Delegatura na Kraj. Reports on concentration camps
        - Auschwitz
          - General (Folder 3)
          - Officers accused of war crimes. Lists (Folder 4)
        - Birkenau
          - General (Folder 5)
          - Letter from (in form of poem) (Folder 6)
        - Majdanek (Folder 7)
        - Pawiak (Folder 8)
        - Ravensbrueck (Folder 9)
      - Ministry of Foreign Affairs. Appeal to the French on behalf of deported Jews (Folder 10)
      - War Crimes Office
        - General (Folder 11)
        - British press review for October and November (Folder 12)
        - Legal adviser
          - Circulated documents (Folder 13)
          - Clippings (Folder 14)
          - Draft of convention on extraditions (Folder 15)
        - List of dossiers (Folder 16)
        - Speeches (Folder 17)
        - Telegrams (Folder 18)
    - International Commission for Penal Reconstruction and Development. Committee on the Rights to be Accorded to Persons Suspected or Accused of Crimes (Folder 19)
    - Supreme Headquarters Allied Expeditionary Forces. Lodz ghetto. Reports (Folder 20)
    - United Nations War Crimes Commission
      - General (Folder 21)
      - Agreement submitted to Polish government (Folder 22)
      - Concentration camps
        - General (Folder 23)
        - Majdanek (Folder 24)
      - Facts Finding Commission, Competence of (Folder 25)
      - Far Eastern and Pacific Subcommission. Polish representative (Folder 26)
      - French declaration of June 10 (Folder 27)
      - List of war criminals
        - "First List (Germans Only)", Dec. (Folder 28)
        - "Second List (Italians)", Dec. (Folder 29)
        - Polish government compiled (Folder 30)
      - Minutes of meetings
        - Nos. 1-30, Oct. 1943- Sept. 1944 (Folder 31)
        - Nos. 31-41, Sept.-Dec. (Folder 32)
      - Polish delegate to (Folder 33)
      - Report on S.A., S.S., and Gestapo (Folder 34)
      - Soviet war criminals (Folder 35)
      - 1945 (Box 108)
    - Government agencies. Polish War Crime Office. Charges nos. 31-34. Typescript (Folder 1)
    - Pro-German propaganda in the United States. Mimeographs (Folder 2)
    - United Nations War Crimes Commission
      - Lists of war criminals. Printed copy
        - "Fourth List of War Criminals together with List of Suspects and Witnesses (Japanese)", March (Folder 3)
        - "Part I. Eighth List of Suspects (Germans). Part III. Third List of Witnesses (Germans)", May (Folder 4)
        - "Third List of War Criminals (Germans)". March (Folder 5)
        - "List of German War Criminals Holding Key Positions", April (Folder 6)
        - "Second List of War Criminals Holding Key Positions (Germany)", May (Folder 7)
        - "Sixth List of War Criminals (Germans)", April (Folder 8)
        - "Part I. Fifth List of War Criminals (Albania, Bulgaria, Hungary, Italy, Romania). Part II. Second List of Suspects (Germans). Part III. Second List of Witnesses (Italians)" (Folder 9)
      - Minutes of meetings, Nos. 42-62, March-May. Mimeograph (Folder 10)
      - Reports, Feb.-May (Folder 11)
- SERIES NO. 245.5. UNITED NATIONS RELIEF AND REHABILITATION ADMINISTRATION
  - 1940. Atlantic Charter. Address of Polish delegation to League of Nations on principles of world's post-war organization (Folder 12)
  - 1941
    - Clippings and press comments (Folder 13)
    - Corrected draft resolution (Folder 14)
    - "Czechoslovak League of Nations Society: Statement on the Transition Period", March 12 (Folder 15)
    - "Deklaracja Roosevelt-Churchill". Report by Michal Potulicki (Folder 16)
    - Diplomatic correspondence with Allied ambassadors (Folder 17)
    - Inter-Allied Conference
      - General (Folder 18)
      - 1941 Committee (Folder 19)
      - Reports from meetings
        - June 12 (Folder 20)
        - September 24 (Folder 21)
      - Sikorski's speech, June 12 (Folder 22)
    - Letters to Anthony Eden from Edward Raczynski Aug. 25 and Aug. 29 (Folder 23)
    - Note to Edward Raczynski handed to Sir Alexander Cadogan on Polish objections to Atlantic Charter (Folder 24)
    - Polish-Czech joint declaration (Folder 25)
    - Polish government response to Charter (Folder 26)
    - Preparations of other Allied governments to Roosevelt-Churchill conference (Folder 27)
    - Report on Charter's controversy by Polish government officials (Folder 28)
    - Response in Poland. Instructions from government (Folder 29)
    - Response to Roosevelt-Churchill meeting. Report from Polish diplomatic sources (Folder 30)
    - Second meeting of Allied governments. Note from Anthony Eden, Aug. 21 (Folder 31)
    - Sekretariat Miedzyaliancki, Polish government concept of (Folder 32)
    - Talks between Anthony Eden, Edward Raczynski, and Wladyslaw Sikorski, Aug. 29 (Folder 33)
  - 1942
    - General (Folder 34)
    - United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration. Declaration of principles. Preparations for talks with H. Lehman (Folder 35)
    - 1943 (Box 109)
    - Allied Post-War Requirements Bureau (Inter-Allied Commission for Post-War Requirements)
      - General (Folder 1)
      - Advisory Committee on Displaced Persons (Folder 2)
      - Clothing and Textile Committee. Need for clothes in post-war Poland (Folder 3)
      - Displaced Population Subcommittee. "Present Location of Displaced Persons". Report (Folder 4)
      - Draft report to Allied governments. Mimeograph (Folder 5)
      - Leith-Ross Committee (Folder 6)
      - Purchase of leather for post-war Poland (Folder 7)
      - Report to Allied governments, June. Printed copy (Folder 8)
    - Canada. Ilsley initiative. Assistance to Poland (Folder 9)
    - United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration
      - General (Folder 10)
      - Analysis of final edition of UNRRA agreement (Folder 11)
      - Draft agreement
        - Allied nations comments (Folder 12)
        - Approaches of different countries. Analysis of diplomatic notes (Folder 13)
        - Additional corrections as proposed by Polish government (Folder 14)
        - Comments by
          - Czechoslovakia (Folder 15)
          - France (Folder 16)
          - Luxemburg (Folder 17)
          - Netherlands (Folder 18)
          - Norway (Folder 19)
          - United States (Folder 20)
          - Yugoslavia (Folder 21)
        - Government response after founding of UNRRA (Folder 22)
  - 1944. United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration (Folder 23)
- SERIES NO. 245.6. INTERNATIONAL MECHANISM OF PAYMENTS
  - 1942. Inter-Allied experts on post-war currency questions. Report of subcommittee, Dec. 22. Typescript (Box 110, Folder 1)
  - 1943
    - General (Folder 2)
    - Argentina. Post-war economy. Report by Miroslaw Arciszewski (Folder 3)
    - Keynes Plan
      - House of Commons debate, May 12. Typescript and clippings (Folder 4)
      - Expert opinion by Jozef Rucinski (Folder 5)
      - International Clearing Union (Folder 6)
      - "Notatka o projekcie organizacji wladz Miedzynarodowego Instytutu Wyplat". Note advising on policy (Folder 7)
      - "Notatka z rozmow wstepnych prowadzonych w Waszyngtonie", July 20. Report by Jozef Rucinski (Folder 8)
      - Swedish response (Folder 9)
    - Morgenthau Plan (Folder 10)
    - United and Associated Nations Stabilisation Fund
      - Correspondence related to (Folder 11)
      - Country quotas (Folder 12)
      - Preliminary draft outline by United States Treasury Department, June 26 (Folder 13)
    - United States. Monetary conference. Telegrams (Folder 14)
    - White Plan. International Investment Bank. Expert opinion by Jozef Rucinski, Sept. 17. Typescript (Folder 15)
  - 1944
    - General (Folder 16)
    - France. "Suggestions Regarding an International Monetary System". Mimeograph (Folder 17)
    - Great Britain. Smaller Nations in World's Economic Life by V. Rand. Pamphlet (Folder 18)
    - Keynes Plan. International Stabilisation Plan
      - "Amerykanski projekt miedzynarodowego banku dla kredytow dlugoterminowych". Expert opinion by T. Janta-Polczynski (Folder 19)